W. L. McAtee Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Research and Writings File, 1803-1963 (Box 45-91)
  - District of Columbia
    - Insects
      - Cercopidae, undated
      - Cicadidae, undated
      - Coleoptera, undated
      - Conopidae, undated
      - Diptera, undated, (2 folders)
      - Hemiptera, 1949, undated, (2 folders)
      - Hymenoptera, undated (Box 57)
      - Lepidoptera, undated
      - Membracidae, undated
      - Miridae, undated, (2 folders)
      - Neuropteroidea, undated
      - Orthopteroidea, undated
      - Other invertebrates, undated
      - Other orders, undated
      - Psyllidae, undated
      - Stratiomyiidae, 1949, undated
    - Notes and background material for
      - "Comparative Abundance of Birds in the District of Columbia Region, 1961-1942," 1951, undated
      - "Flora of the District of Columbia and Vicinity," 1920-1940, undated, (2 folders)
      - A Sketch of the Natural History of the District of Columbia, 1883-1944, undated, (4 folders) (Box 58)
      - "Ten Spring Bird Lists Made Near Washington, D.C.," 1904-1925, undated
    - Robber flies, undated See also Container 68, same heading
    - Vertebrates, undated
    - Winter bird lists, 1913-1931
  - "Eastward Migration Through the Gulf States,"
    - 1942-1943
    - 1944, undated (Box 59)
  - Economic ornithology, lectures, 1939
  - "Economic Tendencies of the Starling," 1943, undated
  - Editing
    - Acknowledgments, 1912-1950
    - Notes, 1904, 1917, undated
  - "Effectiveness in Nature of the So-Called Protective Adaptations in the Animal Kingdom, Chiefly As Illustrated by the Food Habits of Nearctic Birds," tabulation of animal foods, circa 1926, 1949, (2 folders)
  - "Effectiveness in Nature of the So-Called Protective Adaptations in the Animal Kingdom, Chiefly As Illustrated by the Food Habits of Nearctic Birds," tabulation of animal foods, circa 1926, 1949, (4 folders) (Box 60)
  - European game conditions, 1926-1935, undated, circa 1926, 1949
  - Evolution
    - Coloration
      - Plants, 1914-1924, undated
      - Recognition marks, 1910, undated
    - Darwin, criticism of, 1944-1948, undated
    - Effects of environment, 1909-1942, undated, (2 folders) (Box 61)
    - General, 1905-1940, undated, (2 folders)
    - Great age of some organisms, 1915, 1923, undated
    - Insect control by
      - Climate, 1912-1933, undated
      - Parasites, 1908-1935, undated
      - Predators, 1922-1946, undated, (2 folders)
    - Maimed animals, 1906-1944, undated (Box 62)
    - Mutation, 1905-1916, 1933, undated
    - Numbers of insect eggs, plant seeds, etc., 1911-1936, undated
    - Numbers of species, 1910-1926, undated
    - Protective adaptations
      - Animals eating deleterious substances, 1916-1933, undated
      - Beetles, 1901-1921, undated, (2 folders)
      - Experimental study, 1891-1923, undated, (3 folders) (Box 63)
      - General, 1899, 1932-1934, undated
      - Other animals, 1903-1946, undated, (2 folders)
      - Other insects, 1891-1937, undated, (2 folders) (Box 64)
    - Protective coloration
      - General, 1891-1947, undated, (4 folders)
      - General, 1891-1947, undated, (1 folder) (Box 65)
      - Mantis religiosa, 1933, undated
      - Mimicry, 1872-1946, undated, (6 folders)
    - Sexual selection, 1906-1936, undated
    - Variation, 1892-1934, undated (Box 66)
    - Vision in animals, 1917-1947, undated
  - "Evolution of Intelligence," 1897-1911, undated
  - "Feed the Birds This Winter," 1916-1917, undated
  - "A Few of Our Homely Birds and Their Relation to Man," c irca 1899, 1950
  - Field trips See also Container 74, Bloomington
    - Index, 1904-1952
    - Notes, 1896-1953, (2 folders)
    - Notes, 1896-1953, (6 folders) (Box 67)
    - Notes, 1896-1953, (1 folder) (Box 68)
  - Fish-eating birds of the United States, undated
  - Flies
    - Bee flies, circa 1924
    - Crane flies, 1919, undated
    - Horseflies, circa 1918
    - March flies, circa 1921
    - Pomace flies, circa 1924
    - Robber flies, 1917, undated See also Container 58, same heading
    - Scatopsidae, 1916, undated
    - Snipe flies, circa 1931
    - Syrphidae, circa 1916, circa 1924 (Box 69)
  - Folklore of birds
    - Amulets and charms, undated
    - Bibliography, 1913-1947, undated
    - Geographic names, 1940, undated
    - God birds, undated
    - Medicinal uses, undated
    - Miscellany, 1906-1921, undated
    - New World, undated
    - Old World, 1936, undated
    - Omens, undated
    - Weather related, 1906, 1936, undated
  - Fossil specimens identified, undated
  - "Fruits Attractive to Birds" (Box 70)
    - Manuscript and photographs, 1940-1945, undated
    - Notes
      - California, 1935-1940, undated
      - Florida, 1915-1936, undated
      - General, 1940-1945, undated
      - Great Basin states, 1936, undated
      - Northeastern states, 1908-1949, undated, (2 folders)
      - Northern Plains states, 1936-1940, undated
      - Northwestern states, 1913-1940, undated
      - Rocky Mountain states, 1925-1940, undated
      - Southeastern states, 1912, 1936-1940, undated
      - Southern Plains states, 1936-1940, undated (Box 71)
      - Southwestern states, 1936-1940, undated
  - "Fugitive Ornithological Journals," 1915, 1954, undated
  - Game propagation on farms, 1926-1950, undated
  - "Georgian Records in John Latham's General History of Birds, 1821-24," 1942-1945, undated
  - Great Plains shelterbelt project, 1933-1935, undated
  - "Groups of Plants Valuable for Wildlife Utilization and Erosion Control," 1930-1936, undated, (2 folders) (Box 72)
  - Hemiptera
    - Contributions to a chapter on the study of Hemiptera in the United States, 1899-1923, undated
    - European collections, 1927-1933, undated
    - Fabrician types, 1803, 1927, undated
    - Plummer's Island, Md., 1910-1916, undated See also Container 78, same heading, (2 folders)
    - Plummer's Island, Md., 1910-1916, undated, (1 folder) (Box 73)
    - Research proposal, 1920-1921
  - Heteroptera
    - Ambrysus, undated
    - Canopinae and megaridinae, circa 1927
    - Emesidae
      - European collections, 1927-1928, undated
      - Miscellany, undated
    - Geocorinae, undated
    - Hebridae, Veliidae, undated
    - "Heteroptera or True Bugs of Eastern North America," circa 1927
    - Isometopinae, 1931, undated
    - Miscellany, undated
    - Paracalocoris, 1916, undated
    - Piesmidae, undated
    - Thyreocorinae, circa 1927, (2 folders)
  - Homoptera (Box 74)
    - Eupteryginae, undated, (3 folders)
    - Membracidae, undated
    - Miscellany, undated
  - Indiana
    - Bloomington, notes on birds, 1901-1903, (3 folders)
    - Monroe County
      - Migration schedules, 1884-1903
      - Notes by others, circa 1901-1903 (Box 75)
    - Natural history notebooks, circa 1902, (2 folders)
  - Insects
    - Bureau of Entomology, Agriculture Department, identifications by, 1906-1922
    - United States National Museum, Smithsonian Institution, material transferred to, 1915-1928
  - Kirkaldy, George W., library and collections of, 1910-1934
  - Lacey Act, amendments to, 1918-1940
  - Land utilization, 1936-1939 See also Container 45, Land Planning Objectives and Committee on Land Utilization
  - "The Lash-Horn Tree," 1946-1953, undated
  - "Luminosity of Birds," 1928-1947, undated, (2 folders) (Box 76)
  - Martin, A. C., 1935, undated
  - Miscellaneous writings and notes, 1944-1953, undated
  - "Moonstroke," 1944-1947, undated
  - "Mullen Rosettes as Winter Shelters for Insects," circa 1924
  - "Names for Sugar Cane Beer," 1953-1955, undated
  - Nelson, Arnold L., 1935
  - "The North American Birds of George Edwards," 1950, undated
  - "Notes on Drift, Vegetable Balls, and Aquatic Insects as a Food Product of Inland Waters," 1882-circa 1925, undated
  - "Odds and Ends of North American Folklore on Birds" See Container 69, Bibliography
  - "On Scholarly Writing and Critical Reviewing," 1939-1940, undated
  - Ornithological art, 1920, undated
  - Ornithological facetiae, 1905-1936, undated
  - "Pallas's 'Reise,'" 1949, undated (Box 77)
  - Pastime See Container 45, "Account of The Pastime, a Washington Periodical, Largely of Natural History, Published in 1883-85"
  - Personal mail, opening, 1911-1920, undated
  - "A Plan for the Conservation, Restoration, and Management of Wild Life in the United States," 1934, undated
  - Plants
    - Aquatic, 1905-1916, undated
    - Catalogs of collected plants, 1900, 1909-1917
    - For wildlife by forest region, undated
    - Standardization of names, 1936-1938, undated
  - "Plants Useful in Upland Wildlife Management"
    - California, 1936-1937, undated
    - Crop plants for feed patches, 1933-1941, undated
    - Florida, 1936, undated
    - Great Basin states, 1936-1937, undated
    - Northeastern states, 1935-1937, undated
    - Northern Plains states, 1936-1937, undated
    - Northwestern states, 1937, undated
    - Rocky Mountain states, 1937, undated (Box 78)
    - Southeastern states, 1936-1937, undated
    - Southern Plains states, 1936-1937, undated
    - Southwestern states, 1936-1937, undated
  - "Plants Useful to Attract Birds and Protect Fruit," undated
  - "Plants Valuable for Wildlife Utilization and for Erosion Control," 1935-1937
  - Plummer's Island, Md. See also Container 72, same heading
    - Fauna, 1913-1932, undated
    - Fish, 1910-1912, undated
    - Grasshoppers, 1906-1917, undated
  - "Popular Names of Gyrinidæ," 1926, 1945-1947, undated
  - "Possible Check-List Additions from Greenland," 1947, undated
  - "Preservation of Wildlife Along the Potomac," radio talk, 1932
  - President's Committee on Wildlife Restoration, 1933-1934, undated (Box 79)
  - "The Problem: Drained Areas and Wildlife Habitats," 1937-1939
  - Propagation of game birds for food, 1922-1926, undated
  - Propagation of rails, shore birds, and doves, 1929-1930, undated
  - "Providing Occupants for the Model Parks," 1936
  - "A Puzzling Labrador Reference," 1948-1949, undated
  - Rafinesque, Constantine S., 1936-1943
  - A Review of the Nearctic Viburnum
    - Alsographia Americana by C. Rafinesque, notes on, undated
    - Botanic garden, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, N.C., circa 1951
    - Catalog of names given to nearctic forms, undated
    - Correspondence
      - Business, 1951-1956, undated
      - Scientific, 1951-1956
    - Embryology, undated
    - General notes, 1907, 1916, 1952, undated (Box 80)
    - Illustrations, undated, (2 folders)
    - Manuscript, 1953-1955, undated, (2 folders)
    - Printed matter, 1904-1956, (2 folders)
    - References, undated, (2 folders) (Box 81)
    - Sections of the genus, undated
    - Species
      - Acerifolium, 1951, undated, (2 folders)
      - Affine, 1952, undated, (2 folders)
      - Bracteatum, 1908, undated
      - Carolinianum, undated (Box 82)
      - Cassinoides
        - General, undated, (2 folders)
        - Variations, undated
      - Crenatum, undated
      - Dentatum, 1951, undated
      - Edule, undated
      - Ellipticum, undated
      - Grandifolium, undated (Box 83)
      - Indianense, undated
      - Lantana, undated
      - Lentago, undated
      - Molle, undated
      - Nudum, 1951, undated, (2 folders)
      - Obovatum, undated (Box 84)
      - Opulus, undated
      - Ozarkense, undated
      - Plicatum, undated
      - Prunifolium, undated, (2 folders)
      - Pubescens, undated
      - Recognitum, undated, (2 folders)
      - Rufidulum, undated, (2 folders) (Box 85)
      - Scabrellum, 1924, undated, (2 folders)
      - Sieboldi, undated
    - Unidentified forms, undated
  - Rhynchota: Fabrician genotypes, undated
  - Roadrunners, 1905-1932, undated
  - St. Vincent's Island, Fla., 1914-1916, undated
  - Salamanders (Box 86)
    - Ambystoma opacum, 1886-1933, undated, (2 folders)
    - Others, 1907, undated
  - Sapsuckers, 1904-1905, undated See also Container 91, "Woodpeckers in Relation to Trees and Wood Products"
  - "The Shedding of the Stomach Lining by Birds, Particularly as Exemplified by the Anatidae," circa 1917
  - "Showers of Organic Matter," 1911-1942, undated, (2 folders)
  - "Stable Nomenclature," circa 1952
  - Taxonomy, 1884-1936, undated (Box 87)
  - "Thoughts of Great Men on Conservation," 1942, undated
  - "Thoughts on Subspecies," 1941, undated
  - "Torpidity in Birds," 1909-1948, undated, (4 folders)
  - "Trade in Aphrodisiacs Endangers Wildlife," 1937-1951, undated (Box 88)
  - "The Upland Plover's Wind Call," circa 1955
  - "The Value of Wildlife"
    - Big game animals on the national forests, 1923-1931, undated
    - Correspondence, 1926-1934
    - Direct value, 1920-1936, undated, (2 folders)
    - Miscellany, 1924-1941, undated
    - Recreational value, 1923-1936, undated, (2 folders)
    - Typescript, undated (Box 89)
  - Variation in trail markings of Warblers, circa 1904
  - Vermin control, 1930-1940, (2 folders)
  - "Virginia Creeper as a Winter Food for Birds," 1901-1903
  - Waterflow Committee, Agriculture Department, 1934
  - Waterfowl
    - Committee re book on waterfowl, 1931
    - Propagation, 1885-1939, undated, (2 folders)
    - Writings, 1910
  - Whirligig beetles See Container 78, "Popular Names of Gyrinidæ"
  - Wild duck food plants
    - Algal ecology of Iowa lakes, 1934-1936, undated
    - "Aquatic Plants Eaten by the Principal Game Ducks," 1909, 1917, undated
    - Lectures, undated (Box 90)
    - Various topics, 1906-1941, undated
    - Water conveyor, 1928
  - Wildfowl food plants
    - Distribution, 1912-1916, undated
    - Pondweeds, 1905-1925, undated
    - Stomach contents, undated
    - Utilization, undated
    - Wild celery, 1904-1909, undated
    - Wild rice, 1901-1932, undated
  - Wildlife as a replacement crop, 1933-1934
  - "Wildlife Conservation" See also Container 77, "A Plan for the Conservation, Restoration, and Management of Wild Life in the United States"
    - Manuscripts, 1938-1951, undated, (2 folders)
    - Notes, 1925-1940, undated (Box 91)
  - "Woodpecker Economics," 1905-1909, undated
  - "Woodpeckers in Relation to Trees and Wood Products," 1897-1932, undated, (3 folders)
- Handwriting Collection, 1847-1945 (Box 92-101)
  Correspondence, notes, and memorabilia.
  Arranged alphabetically by scientific field or subject and by name of person therein.
  - Botanists, 1875-1945, undated, (4 folders) (Box 92)
  - Bureau of Biological Survey, Agriculture Department, 1900-1945, undated, (5 folders) (Box 93)
  - Entomologists, 1847-1945, undated (Box 94)
    - A-O, (5 folders)
    - P-Z, (3 folders) (Box 95)
  - Mammalogists, 1883-1944, (2 folders)
  - Miscellaneous scientists, 1881-1945, undated, (6 folders) (Box 96)
  - Non-scientists, 1881-1945, undated, (5 folders) (Box 97)
  - Ornithologists, 1860-1944, undated (Box 98)
    - A-F, (6 folders)
    - G-M, (7 folders) (Box 99)
    - N-S, (5 folders) (Box 100)
    - T-Z, (3 folders) (Box 101)
  - Wildlife Society, 1927-1945, undated, (2 folders)
- Miscellany, 1881-1961 (Box 102-116)
  Records of the Bureau of Biological Survey, miscellaneous avocational writings by McAtee, calendars, memorabilia, diaries, scrapbook, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically therein.
  - Appointments and promotions, 1903-1949 (Box 102)
  - Bureau of Biological Survey, Agriculture Department
    - Correspondence, 1888-1918, undated, (6 folders)
    - Field work (Box 103)
      - Correspondence, 1908-1930, (3 folders)
      - Reports, 1934-1938, undated, (3 folders)
    - Malleis, Harry See also Container 8, same heading
      - Correspondence, 1923-1941, (3 folders)
      - H.E. Coffin Fund, 1924-1927, undated
      - Reports (Box 104)
        - By McAtee, circa 1927
        - Weekly activities, 1923-1924
      - Vouchers, 1923-1924
    - Office memoranda
      - 1910-1931, (10 folders)
      - 1932-1949, (11 folders) (Box 105)
    - Report on the work of the Division of Economic Ornithology and Mammalogy, predecessor to the Bureau of Biological Survey, 1886-1887
  - Calendars (Box 106)
    - 1936-1942, (6 folders)
    - 1943-1948, (6 folders) (Box 107)
    - 1949 (Box 108)
  - Diaries, 1905-1910
  - Memorabilia, 1900-1961, undated, (3 folders)
  - Miscellaneous avocational writings by McAtee (Box 109)
    - Autobiography (birth through college), 1893-1904, undated, (6 folders)
    - "Cundumana," 1924-1954, undated
    - "The Cynara Complex," 1930-1932, undated
    - Dialectal speech (Box 110)
      - General, 1953, undated
      - "Grant County, Indiana, Speech and Song," 1936-1955, undated, (2 folders)
    - "Dictionaries and the Supreme Authority Claim," 1954, undated
    - Golf, articles on, 1924-1929, undated
    - "Hair of a Roman Lady," 1933
    - "Late Thoughts," 1932-1945, undated
    - "Measured and Unmeasured," circa 1944
    - "Mind, Heart, and Soul," circa 1927, 1950, undated
    - Miscellaneous
      - Poetry and prose, 1912-1955, undated, (3 folders)
      - Poetry and prose, 1912-1955, undated, (13 folders) (Box 111)
      - Printed writings, 1948-1955 (Box 112)
    - "Nomina Abitera," 1937-1954, undated, (5 folders)
    - Notes
      - Anthologies, 1953
      - Composition and criticism, undated
      - Keats, John, 1949-1953, undated
      - Poets and poetry, 1938-1951, undated
      - Writing, 1908-1947, undated (Box 113)
    - Poems
      - Love, undated
      - Passion, 1911-1934
    - Reviews
      - American poets, circa 1950-circa 1953, (4 folders)
      - British poets, 1949-circa 1953, (2 folders)
    - "Saint Burroughs," 1907-1945, undated (Box 114)
    - "Supplements to Rabelais," 1921, 1938
    - "Ten Tales," 1912-1918
    - Unused themes, 1914-1950, undated
    - "What Women Poets Think About It," undated
  - Printed matter
    - 1881-1900, (2 folders)
    - 1923-1935, undated, (4 folders) (Box 115)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1894-circa 1900 (Box 116)
  - Wills, 1915-1954